<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mount Pisgah a sermon preached at the publick thanksgiving, February xiiii, 1688/9, for Englands deliverance from popery &amp;c. upon Deut. 3. 24, 25 / by J.F. ...</title>
            <author>Flavel, John, 1630?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23001</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14872633</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206130</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240947156</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1171</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">14872633</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1570:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mount Pisgah a sermon preached at the publick thanksgiving, February xiiii, 1688/9, for Englands deliverance from popery &amp;c. upon Deut. 3. 24, 25 / by J.F. ...</title>
                  <author>Flavel, John, 1630?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Matthew Wotton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy III, 24-25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Thanksgiving Day addresses.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206130:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206130:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MOƲNT PISGAH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Publick Thanksgiving <hi>February</hi> xiiij, 1688/9.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Englands</hi> Deliverance from Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon <hi>Deut.</hi> 3.24, 25.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi> Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 142.2.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord doth build up Jerusalem, he gathereth together the out-casts of Israel.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISA. 66.10.</hi>
               </bibl> Rejoyce ye with Jerusalem, and be glad with her, all ye that love her; rejoyce with joy with her, all ye that mourn for her.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>Nullum officium referenda gratia magis necessarium.</hi>
               <bibl>Cicero 1. de Offic.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Matthew Wotton</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> near St. <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:206130:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206130:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>GEORGE</hi> Earl of <hi>Southerland,</hi> Lord <hi>Strathnaver,</hi> Heritable Lord of Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and Sheriff in the Shire of <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was a sweet refreshment to me in the dayes of our late Exile to be providentially cast into your Lordships Company and Acquaintance. I savoured in your self, and your most accomplished Lady, those things which are rarely found in persons of your eminent station and quality in the World.</p>
            <p>I have neither forgotten your tender sympathy with poor distressed Zion, nor my weak endeavours to prop up your Faith with respect to a more chearful aspect of Providence upon the Churches.</p>
            <p>And now my Lord, we that mourned for, and suffered with <hi>Sion;</hi> are this day called to rejoyce with her. Yea, you are called to rejoyce with a joy above the common joy, in as much as your Lordship is not only a partaker of the common mercy with others, but God hath honoured you in accompanying and assisting the glorious Instrument of our Deliverance.</p>
            <p>My Lord, It is a greater honour to be serviceable to the Interest of Christ, than to descend from the blood of Nobles. 'Tis the honour of Angels that they are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string
<pb facs="tcp:206130:3"/>Spirits for the Churches good. What my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of and expectations from this providence are, your Lordship will measure from the following discourse.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>England</hi> rejoyce to behold a Protestant King upon its Throne: A King that gives more Honour to the Throne, than it is capable to reflect on him that sits thereon. His soundness in Protestant Principles, his Prudence and Equity in Government, his zeal for the Interest of Christ at the lowest ebb; speak him such a blessing to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as for Ages past it hath not enjoyed: And now my Lord, we may expect if ever, to find that glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of a just and holy King answered in him, that he shall be to us as the light of the Morning, when the Sun riseth, even a morning without Clouds, <hi>&amp;c. 2 Sam. 23.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, Having in my place performed that Duty of Thanksgiving to God, enjoyned by publick Authority, with the same alacrity that <hi>Moses</hi> his Mother obeyed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Pharaoh's Daughter,</hi> to nurse her own Child; I am bold (notwithstanding the imperfections that attend it) to offer it in all humility to your Lordships hands; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confident the design of it will be agreeable to your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, though there be nothing of External Ornament to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to your fancy. So heartily congratulating your Lordships safe and happy return, with your pious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Lady, in the memorable year of Englands Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the Romish Yoak, I beg your Honours pardon for this presumption, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours most Obliged Servant to Command, <hi>J. FLAVELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206130:3"/>
            <head>MOUNT PISGAH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. 3.24, 25.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               </bibl>
               <q>O Lord God, thou hast begun to shew thy Servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand; for what God is there in heaven, or in earth, that can do according to thy works, and according to thy might? I pray thee let me go over and see the good land that is beyond Jordan, that goodly Mountain, and Lebanon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TIS the Observation of a Learned Man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> T. Goodwin <hi>in Apoc. p.</hi> 189.</note> that the Revolution of an Hundred Years hath produced (especially in these latter times) new Motions and Alterations in the Church, like unto those that fell out an Hundred Years before. So it was in <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia. John Hus</hi> at the stake, about the year 1417, uttered this remarkable speech, <hi>After an hundred years you Papists shall be called to an account.</hi> The <hi>Bohemians</hi> caused <hi>post centum annos</hi> to be stampt upon their Coin,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206130:4"/>for the preservation of so memorable a Prediction; and accordingly an Hundred Years after, <hi>viz.</hi> 1517. <hi>Luther</hi> arose, and with him the Reformation. It hath been so in <hi>England.</hi> Our Fathers deservedly set a signal remembrance upon the year 1588, <hi>Annus octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesimus octavus est Annus mirabilis;</hi> the year <hi>Eighty Eight</hi> is a wonderful year, and it was so indeed, for then the Lord defeated the formidable Enemies of his Cause and People with a mighty hand, and an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stretched arm upon the great Waters. Then did <hi>England</hi> sing his Praises, saying, <hi>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, among the Gods? Who is like unto thee, glorious in holiness, fearful in praises, doing wonders?</hi> Exod. 15.11.</p>
            <p>A full <hi>Century</hi> is now run out since that year of Wonders, wherein we have reaped the precious and inestimable fruits of that years Mercy. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the great ingratitude of this Nation for all the Civil and Spiritual Mercies it hath enjoyed in consequence to that Mercy, whereby God hath been highly provoked to say to <hi>England</hi> as he did to <hi>Israel, Judg.</hi> 10.13. <hi>I will deliver you no more,</hi> yet behold another <hi>Eighty Eight</hi> crowned and enriched with Mercies, no less admirable and glorious than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; a year for which the Children yet unborn shall praise the Lord.</p>
            <p>You are called this day to rejoice, I am not only called to rejoyce with you in the Publick Mercies of this day; but also to direct you to the best way of improving the Mercies you rejoice in, that they may prove introductive to greater Mercies than themselves. To that end I have chosen this Scripture which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains both Parts of the Work and Duty of the Day.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:206130:4"/>
            <p>The Text contains the sum of <hi>Moses</hi> his Prayer at <hi>Edrei,</hi> after the signal Victory God there gave him over the last Enemy that forbad his passage to the Confines of <hi>Canaan.</hi> This <hi>Edrei,</hi> was a Town on this side <hi>Jordan,</hi> scituate in the fruitful Country of <hi>Bashan,</hi> near unto that famous River by which it was divided from the Land of Promise, and afterwards fell to the lot of <hi>Manasseh.</hi> Hither <hi>Moses</hi> had led the People, and now it was but one remove more, (their passage over <hi>Jordan</hi>) and they should finish their wearisom peregrination, and arrive at the desire of their hearts, even rest and settlement in that good Land the Lord had promised them. And here you may see how swift and strong the motion of <hi>Moses</hi> his spirit in Prayer is, now it was come so nigh the <hi>Centre,</hi> almost in sight of that pleasant Land, where God intended to settle his Worship and record his Name. <hi>O Lord thou hast begun to shew thy Servant thy greatness,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I pray thee let me go over, and see the good land that is beyond Jordan, that goodly mountain, and Lebanon.</hi> Wherein note,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Mercy pray'd for.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Argument pleaded to obtain it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Mercy <hi>Moses</hi> prayes for, that he might go over, and see the good Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The good land was <hi>Canaan,</hi> called the glory of all Lands, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.6. it was a glorious land in respect of its natural Fertility and amaenity; but much more glorious in respect of the Presence of God in his Ordinances. And therefore above all the pleasant sights in <hi>Canaan,</hi> he desires to see <hi>that goodly mountain,</hi> that is <hi>Mount Moriah,</hi> on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206130:5"/>which <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up his onely son <hi>Isaac,</hi> and whereon by the Spirit of Prophecy <hi>Moses</hi> foresaw the glorious Temple was to be built, whither the Tribes should go up to Worship, even the Tribes of the Lord unto the Testimony of <hi>Israel.</hi> There were to be the Symbols of his Presence, and the House of Prayer for all People. There the Ark was to rest, and all the Promises made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seed to be fulfilled. This inflames the desires of <hi>Moses,</hi> (now upon the very borders) to have a sight of that goodly Mountain, and <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that famous Forest so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in Scripture, of whose stately Cedars the Glorious Temple was to be built, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 5.6, 9. This desire of <hi>Moses</hi> was not from any superstitious opinion he had of the holiness of the place, in respect of the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> whose bones were laid in that land, (as some <hi>Popish</hi> Glosses would have it) but he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desired to see the accomplishment of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises now so nigh the birth, by the actual possession of that good land. This was the Mercy he pray'd for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how could <hi>Moses</hi> desire to go over <hi>Jordan</hi> into this good Land, when God had before so expresly told him he should not. <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12. <hi>And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron, because ye believed me not, to sanctifie me in the eyes of the Children of Israel, therefore ye shall not bring this Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the land which I have given them.</hi> Did this Holy Man suffer his desires to transport him beyond his Duty, to go further than God would have him?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:206130:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> No, he did not, but not being sure the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was absolute, but might be such a one as was made of <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> Death, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.1. or of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevehs</hi> Destruction, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.4. there was room for Prayer. You see the Mercy <hi>Moses</hi> pray'd for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us next consider the Argument by him pleaded for the obtaining of his suit, and that is taken from the whole series of former Mercies which were all introductive to this remaining and compleating Mercy, the planting of them in the Land of Promise. <hi>O Lord God, thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy greatness, and thy mighty hand,</hi> &amp;c. Where note,</p>
            <p n="1">1. His most thankful acknowledgement and magnifying of past and present Mercies. His Eyes were not so dazled with the splendour of Mercy to come, and in a near expectation, as to overlook the former or present Mercies as small and inconsider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. No, he lifts up the name of God in his Praises for them, and tells him he had begun to shew him his Greatness in them. They are great in <hi>Moses</hi>'s Eye, and he expresses a suitable sense of them. He well knew the way to engage further Mercies is thankfully to acknowledge and magnifie past and present ones. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. He rests not there, but improves these begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Mercies, and pleads them in his Argumentative Prayer for the consummating and perfecting Mercies yet to come, <hi>q. d.</hi> Lord thy works are perfect, thou dost not use to begin and not to finish, as Men do; to bring to the birth, and not cause to bring forth: The Gods of the Heathen are a lye, and vanity, but thou art the true God, and thy Promises are Truth it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206130:6"/>self. Now Lord in pursuance of thy promises, to <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> thou hast begun to fulfil the Mercy promised, <hi>Israel</hi> is brought with Signs and Wonders and a mighty hand out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and upon the very borders of the Land, Lord compleat the work now in giving them the possession of it, and for me Lord, I pray thee (if it be thy Will) let me enter with them, and as I have had my part in the troubles of <hi>Egypt,</hi> straights and Tryals these Forty Years in the Desert; let me take my part also in the Joy, Rest and Comfort of that blessed Land to which I am now come so nigh. This seems to be the sense and meaning of <hi>Moses</hi> Prayer. Divers Excellent points of Doctrine naturally offer themselves from the Text, as</p>
            <p>
               <label>Doctrine I.</label>
               <hi>That the rest and prosperity of the Church is a very desirable Mercy in the eyes of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any thing will make a Christian desirous to abide on Earth, next to the finishing of the work of Grace on him, and the work of Obedience by him, this is the thing, <hi>Psal.</hi> 106.4, 5. <hi>Remember me O Lord, with the favour that thou bearest unto thy people; O visit me with thy salvation: that I may see the good of thy chosen, that I may rejoyce with the gladness of thy nation; that I may glory with thine inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Doctrine II.</label>
               <hi>How desireable soever it be to see the Churches Glory
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206130:6"/>and Prosperity on Earth, yet the greatest and best of Saints may be denied it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moses</hi> the Saint of God, the Favorite of Heaven, earnestly desired the sight of this Mercy, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it. Get thee up to Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> saith God, and dye there, thou shalt not go over <hi>Jordan,</hi> and yet <hi>Moses</hi> was no loser by it. Though God shut him out of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he took him into Heaven. We read <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.17. of that blessed day when Christ was among men in the flesh, Preaching, Praying and Working Miracles, that many Prophets and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men desired to see those things which they saw (among whom he walked) and saw them not, and to hear the things which they heard, but did not hear them, <hi>Demarathus</hi> of <hi>Corinth</hi> was wont to say, that those <hi>Grecians</hi> lost a great part of the Comfort of their Lives, that had not seen great <hi>Alexander</hi> sitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Darius</hi> his Throne, St. <hi>Augustine</hi> wished to have seen three things, <hi>Rome</hi> in its glory, <hi>Paul</hi> in the face, and Christ in the Flesh. But we must not be our own choosers, it shall be given to them for whom it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. But I stay not upon either of these, there are two other points in the Text which invite my Thoughts and Discourse this day; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Doctrine III.</label>
               <hi>That great Mercies received (though there be yet greater than they to be expected) call for an answerable sense and acknowledgement in the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:206130:7"/>
            <p>
               <label>Doctrine IV.</label>
               <hi>That the beginnings of Mercy and Deliverance to the Church are convertible into so many Pleas and Arguments in prayer for the perfection and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summation thereof.</hi> I begin with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Doctrine III.</label>
               <hi>That great Mercies received (though there be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they to be expected) call for an answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able sense and acknowledgment in the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moses</hi> magnifies the Mercies received in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in the <hi>Wilderness</hi> at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and at <hi>Edrei,</hi> as things wherein God had begun to show him his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and his mighty hand, things on which God had visibly stampt and impressed his Greatness: though he still expected greater things to come. 'Twas <hi>Elihu</hi>'s Counsel to <hi>Job</hi> with respect to Gods providential pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with him, <hi>Job</hi> 36.24. <hi>Remember that thou magnifie his work which men behold. Elihu</hi> thought it to be <hi>Jobs</hi> Duty (and doubtless it was so) to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie or lift up the name of God even under afflictive providences, to exalt God when God cast him down; but you are called this day to magnifie the work of God in comfortable providences, and to lift up his Name, whilst he is lifting you up in Deliverances, and chearful providences. 'Tis true, we cannot mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any work of God by making any addition to it, or making it greater than it is; but we should mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206130:7"/>every work of God, by giving it its full dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions in our Considerations of it, and suitable affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to it. <hi>The works of the Lord are great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein, Psal.</hi> 111.2. We then magnifie them, when we search them out, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and weigh them in all their circumstances, and this must needs afford singular pleasure to a sanctified soul. Oh 'tis sweet to trace the footsteps of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long those pleasant paths of Mercy and Salvation, wherein he hath walked towards his Church, or our selves in particular. Two things invite our thoughts to dwell upon them at this time.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What makes a work of Mercy truly great.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>What is that suitable sense we should have of such Works.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What are the things that make any Work of Mercy truly great?</p>
            <p>Now there are seven Considerations or properties of a work of Mercy which make it great indeed. If but one or two of these be found upon such a work, it deserves the name of great, but if there be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of them all in any Work of God, as there is in that work which we celebrate this day. O how great will it then appear!</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Then doth a Work of Mercy or Deliverance deserve the name of great and magnificent, when it involves our spiritual as well as our Civil and Natural Comforts and Enjoyments in it, and rescues our Souls as well as our Bodies from Ruine and Misery.</p>
            <p>Temporal Mercies have their value, 'tis no small Mercy to have our Estates, Liberties, and lives secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Rapine and Violence. <hi>Deborah</hi> celebrated this Mercy in her Song of Praise, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.6, 7, 11.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206130:8"/>
               <hi>In the dayes of Shamgar the son of Anath, in the dayes of Jael; the high wayes were unoccupied, and the Travellers walked through by-wayes. The inhabitants of the Villages ceased in Israel, untill that I deborah arose, that I arose a mother in Israel. They that are delivered from the noise of Archers in the places of drawing water; there shall they rehearse the righteous acts of the Lord, even the righteous acts towards the inhabitants of his villages in Israel: then shall the people of the Lord go down to the gates.</hi> 'Twas a sad time in <hi>Israel,</hi> when they were barr'd from their Fountains, and forced to creep through By-wayes and Woods by Night for fear of the Enemy. When the course of Justice was stopt, and there were no Judges in the Gates: Therefore the People are here excited to praise the Lord for their Deliverance from these Calamities.</p>
            <p>But 'tis a far greater Misery to be cut off from the Wells of Salvation, barr'd from the Springs of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; forced to creep through By and Obscure wayes to get bread to relieve their Souls; to have our Teachers driven into Corners; which hath been the Case of Gods People for many years in <hi>England:</hi> Now, to be delivered from such Miseries, is a Mercy above all value.</p>
            <p>Liberty to serve the Lord without fear, liberty without a snare or hook in it, and a well setled dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble liberty, for such is that we may now (if ever) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise our selves; what soul can dilate it self wide enough, to take in the adequate sense of such a Mercy? We were glad of Liberty from our Enemies, when we sought it not; we peaceably and thankfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd it, though just Fears and Jealousies much dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Lustre of it: But the Lord in this dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206130:8"/>of his Providence will I hope so establish the just Liberties of his People, that it shall never be in the power of violent and wicked men any more to oppress them. There was a time when the Witnesses of Christ lay dead, and their Enemies rejoyced over them; the Lord hath begun to revive them, and the time (I trust), even the appointed time is at hand, when <hi>they shall hear a great voice from heaven (jussu Supremi magistratus,</hi> saith learned <hi>Mede</hi>) saying, <hi>Come up hither.</hi> And both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> shall rejoyce together in their Spiritual as well as Civil Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Mercies. What Soul that loves Jesus Christ in sincerity doth not feel it self chear'd and raised in proportion to the Hopes and Evidences it hath of the approach of so great and desireable a Mercy?</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Then is any work of Mercy and Deliverance to the Church deservedly stiled <hi>great,</hi> when it is wrought out in an <hi>extraordinary way,</hi> and the singer of God is evidently seen therein. Thus it was with <hi>Israel</hi> in their Introduction into the Land of Promise, <hi>Psal.</hi> 44.3. <hi>For they got not the land in possession by their own sword, neither did their own arm save them; but thy right hand, and thine arm, and the light of thy countenance; because thou hadst a favour unto them.</hi> It was not by the strength of their own arm, or the length of their own Sword that they subdued and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd; no, it was a smile of Providence that did the work. The finger of God in Providence appears in the secret influences of God upon the spirits of men, infusing Courage into the hearts of some, and sending faintness into the spirits of others, so that the feeble
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206130:9"/>become as <hi>David,</hi> when mean while the men of might cannot find their hands. This lifts up the Wheels above the Earth, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The sudden production of Mercy magnifies it. Mercies are highly to be prized how long soever we wait for them; but when they come surprizingly, they come with great advantage upon us, and have for that, the more ravishing sweetness in them, <hi>Psal.</hi> 126.1, 2, 3. <hi>When the Lord turned again the captivity of Sion, we were like them that dream. Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with singing; then said they among the heathen, the Lord hath done great things for them. The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</hi> The change was so great, so sudden, that it amazed them, they took it rather for a <hi>Phantome</hi> that deluded their Senses, than for a reality. The deliverance was incredible, they could not believe themselves to be delivered, when they really were delivered. They fancied when they came to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that it was rather a pleasant dream of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> in <hi>Babylon;</hi> than so indeed. Are we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed set at liberty to Worship God at <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> or are we mocked with a dream, and deluded with a pleasant Fancy of such a Mercy? So again we read, <hi>Isa.</hi> 66.8, 9. <hi>Who hath heara such a thing? Who hath seen such things? shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day? or shall a nation be born at once? For assoon as Sion travelled she brought forth her children.</hi> What, Sow and Reap in the same day! The birth to antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the pangs of Travail! Who hath seen or heard such things saith the <hi>Prophet?</hi> Surely <hi>England</hi> hath seen it this day. <hi>Cardinal Pool</hi> once abused this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206130:9"/>in his Letter to Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the third, applying it to the sudden change of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Popery</hi> in the beginning of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign. But we are called this day to sanctifie the Name of God in a work of Providence, wherein the Lord hath indeed fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it before our eyes. So great and sudden! <hi>Great and marvellous are thy works, O Lord God Almighty, just and true are thy wayes, O thou King of Saints.</hi> Generations to come will think we do but hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize, when they shall read the one half of the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our dayes.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) When one Mercy is an introductive leading Mercy to many more, that are greater than it self; that Mercy which is so, though in it self it were never so small; well deserves the Title of a great Mercy; and may we not judge the present Mercy to be such? In the rending off these Kingdoms from Antichrist, the tenth part of the great City is visibly fallen. <hi>Rome</hi> hath paid her Tenths to Christ already, and that as an earnest of the whole, which is shortly to fall into his hands. <hi>Rome</hi>'s Glass was turned up by Christ more than 1200 years past, and in the Judgment of very many Learned and Searching men, is now almost run down. <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath lately had a Triumph, and said, <hi>I sit as a Queen and shall not see widowhood, or loss of children any more.</hi> The Kings of the Earth have given <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their force of Armes, and power of Lawes unto the <hi>Beast.</hi> But the Lord hath begun to shake Heaven and Earth, that the things which are made may be shaken down, and so to ruin him by the same means he first arose. He is taking to himself his Power and Reign, that the Kingdom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206130:10"/>and dominion under the whole Heavens may be the Lords, and that work of Providence which we cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate this day, appears to me a great step towards it. Call it <hi>Gad,</hi> for a Troop follows it. The World hath found, and shall still find much Truth in that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the Learned Dr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> More<hi>'s My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of Godliness</hi> lib. 5. cap. 17. <hi>Printed</hi> Anno 1660.</note>
               <hi>More,</hi>
               <q>I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed (saith he) to profess, that I think it clear out of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> that the Scene of things in <hi>Christendom,</hi> will in a short time be very much changed for the better; the time of the Churches appearing that is truly <hi>Apostolical</hi> both in Life and Doctrine, appears by the computation of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies to be very near at hand, when the Witnesses shall rise, and the Woman come out of the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, and the Kingdoms of the World shall be the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Christ, and he shall reign for ever and ever. There is no stability to be expected in the Kingdoms of Men, (but Vengeance will ever and anon flow in upon them) till that City be raised whose not only Foundation is laid in twelve, but whose Gates, Tribes, Angels, the breadth and height of the Wall, and the solid continent of the whole City, are nothing else but a replication still of twelve throughout: That is to say, till that Church ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear which is purely Apostolical in Doctrine and Worship.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> is said to be the first Kingdom that receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Gospel with the Countenance of Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. This was its Honour, and to be the first that breaks off from Antichrist will be as great an Honour as the former. The rest are to follow in their order. O what a leading Mercy is the mercy of this Day!</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:206130:10"/>(5.) Then may a Work of God be stiled great and magnificent, when the Lord carries it on through great Difficulties and seeming Impossibilities. The greater the difficulties in the way, the greater must the mercy be when it arrives to us through them all. Thus came the <hi>Israelites</hi> into the Land of Promise, <hi>Psal.</hi> 66.12. <hi>Thou causedst men to ride over our heads; we went through sire and through water; but thou brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test us out into a wealthy place.</hi> To pass through Fire and Water, is a Proverbial Speech, noting the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test difficulties and deadly dangers. Such was that at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> a deliverance out of such dangers, may be called Life out of Death, and such have our Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances been. Our Enemies had grasped all power in their hands; and were full of considence. They were folden together as Thorns, and drunk as Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards; as the Prophet expresses it, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.10. Strong Combinations, and answerable Confidence and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Event; but when the time of Mercy was come, Armies, Navies, Counsels, Forreign Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, and all give way to the design of Mercy. And what are all the Mountains before <hi>Zerubabel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) That which exceedingly greatens a Mercy or Deliverance is the <hi>seasonableness</hi> thereof. When it nicks the proper Season; comes in the most oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune time; <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36. <hi>The Lord shall judg his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and repent himself for his servants; when he seeth that their power is gone, and that there is none shut up, or left.</hi> The Lord suffers the Danger to come to an extremity, and then in the Mount of difficulties and streights he appears. If deliverance should come fooner, it would be less valued, and if later, it would
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206130:11"/>come too late for our comfort. He is a God of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all his Works are made beautiful by their seasonableness, How the Case stood with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Interest in <hi>Europe,</hi> when God began to stir up the Spirits of the Princes to commiserate and relieve it; we all know our Enemies looked upon us as their sure prey, and we could not but look upon our selves in great hazard, The Lord suffered the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief conceived to go to the parturient fulness of its time, and then gave it a miscarrying Womb. Who is like unto the Lord? and what works are like his Works!</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) In a word, then is a work of Mercy truely great, when it brings forth invaluable Blessings at a cheap rate. When Enjoyments and Comforts more worth than our lives, come at easie rates to our hands.</p>
            <p>You read, <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Every battel of the Warrior is with confused noise and garments roll'd in blood.</hi> War is terrible and costly, especially Civil Wars. When a Nation like a Candle lighted at both ends, quickly consumes and melts down in the middle. There are confused noises in Battels, terrible to hear. The thundering of Drums, and sound of Trumpets; the neighing of Horses, and shouts of Armies; the roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Cannons, the Shrieks and Groans of dying Men; these are confused noises indeed, and yet its worth enduring all this to hear the joyful sound of the Gospel, and preserve the pure Reformed Religion in the midst of us: 'Twere better part with our Blood than the Gospel; exhaust our Treasure, and leave our Children poor, than devest them of the best of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206130:11"/>Blessings, and leave them to be train'd up in Idolatry, and stretch out their hands to a strange God.</p>
            <p>But lo what hath God wrought for <hi>England!</hi> You have those Mercies that have cost others dear, and they have cost you nothing. You have sold your selves for nothing, and are redeemed without price. Your God hath been liberal in Mercy, but sparing of Blood. Such Mercies, so many Mercies without a stroke! according to this time it shall be said, <hi>What hath God wrought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you see what those Mercies are wherein God shews his Greatness.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the next place let us consider what that sutable sense, or those answerable impressions are, which such great Mercies call for. <hi>Moses</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> expresses a very becoming sense of the great things God had begun to do for him and his people; Oh that there were such an heart in us this day. Now there are five things wherein the comely behaviour of our Souls towards God under great Mercies doth consist.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) In our Eying the Hand of God in the Mercy, and thankful Ascriptions of all the Glory and Praise to his Name. So doth <hi>Moses</hi> in the <hi>Text, Thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy greatness and thy mighty hand.</hi> The <hi>Israelites</hi> were a great Host, Six Hundred Thousand Men that marched out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> an Army sufficient to invade and subdue a far greater Country than <hi>Canaan</hi> was; but <hi>Moses</hi> looks off from them and ascribes all their Successes and Victories to the Hand of God. Not my <hi>mighty host,</hi> but <hi>thy mighty hand.</hi> God affects not social Glory; the dividing of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206130:12"/>Praise, forfeits the Mercy. He that doth all in us and for us, expects justly the Praise and Glory of all from us. <hi>Psal.</hi> 115.1. <hi>Not unto us, not unto us, but to thy name give glory.</hi> Here's a double Negative, and no more than need; for there is double danger of the Creatures invading the Rights of Heaven, and sacrilegious Usurpation of Gods peculiar Praise. Let us therefore look off from Armies, and Navies, from the prudent Conduct and Courage of Men; and see the hand of God in all the great and marvellous things wrought in the midst of us this day.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) 'Tis decorous and suitable to great Mercies, to have our hearts filled with a joy and chearfulness answerable to them. Praise is comely for the upright. As it would be our sin not to mourn when God smites and rebukes us, so will it also not to rejoyce when he chears and comforts us. 'Tis not our <hi>Liberty</hi> only, but our <hi>Duty</hi> to rejoyce in such works of Mercy as these are, <hi>Isa.</hi> 65.18. <hi>But be ye glad and rejoyce for ever in that which I create, for behold I create Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem a rejoycing, and her people a joy.</hi> Methinks Joy should not be under a Christians Command, when he sees what God is creating for <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> As the Morning Stars sang together, and all the Sons of God shouted for joy at the Creation of the World; so should all his Sons and Daughters sing and shout at this new Creation, of the new Heavens, and the new Earth.</p>
            <p>Mistake not here, I call you not to rejoyce in the Miseries or Calamities that are come upon any this day; much less at the Calamities of our late Soveraign. He that searcheth my Heart, knows I commiserate his Condition, and from my soul desire the Lord to bless
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206130:12"/>his Afflictions to his Illumination, and Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But that which you are to rejoyce in this day, is the advancement of Christs Interest in the World, and the Salvation of his Church from the imminent dangers it was so lately under; and the prospect the Lord now gives you of far greater mercies to his People, than ever yet they enjoyed. These are the proper Objects of our Rejoycing.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Then have we a becoming sense of great mercies, when those mercies kindly thaw and melt our hearts into Repentance for Sin, and a sense of our great unworthiness of them. When we abase our selves under exalting Providences. We greatly mistake our selves if we think <hi>England</hi> hath obliged God to be thus peculiarly favourable to it. 'Tis astonishing to think, that a Nation so swarming with <hi>Drunkards, Persecutors, Formalists</hi> in Religion, yea, <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>Scoffers</hi> at all practical and serious Piety; should nevertheless be thus favoured, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and exalted in mercy above all the Nations round about us. I know God hath a great number of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and upright hearted ones in <hi>England,</hi> that have sighed and cried for the Abominations committed in the midst thereof; but so far are they from <hi>arrogating</hi> that they are every where <hi>admiring</hi> the Goodness of God in unexpected mercies. They think, if he had given them their lives for a prey in some obscure corner of the World, he had done more for them than they could justly have expected. Or if he had furnisht them with a sufficient stock of Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to stand quietly at the stake, and have glorified him in the midst of the Flames; he had done above whatever they had deserved at his hands: but to be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206130:13"/>delivered from all those Fears, to sit down in Peace amidst pure Gospel Ordinances, and to look on all these but as the beginnings of Mercy; the dawning of a more bright and glorious day, than ever yet this sinful Nation enjoyed: this I say is melting and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling indeed, to all gracious Spirits. 'Tis a lovely sight to see the Tears of Repentance overtaking the Tears of Joy and Thankfulness; Sighs and Blushes for Sin, mixed with Smiles and Rejoycings in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Then do we answer the voice of Mercy and discover a suitable sense of it, when it strongly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to new Obedience, and more exactness in walking with God for time to come. We find an excellent Example of both these effects of Mercy, <hi>viz:</hi> Repentance for past Sins, and Resolutions for new Obedience, in the 79 <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. and 13. <hi>ver. Remember not against us former iniquities,</hi> saith <hi>Asaph,</hi> that was the frame of his heart as to past sins; and then <hi>ver.</hi> 13. as to the future, if he would let <hi>the sighing of the Prisoners to come before him, and deliver those that were appointed to dye,</hi> as he speaks <hi>ver.</hi> the 11th. Then saith he, <hi>We thy people, and the sheep of thy pasture will give thee thanks for ever, we will shew forth thy praise to all generations.</hi> O <hi>England, England!</hi> thy God this Day calls thee to thy Knees, though it be thy Day of Thanksgiving, and rejoycing. He expects to see thy Tears upon thy Cheeks this day for thy former iniquities, and that thou bind thy self to thy God with these bonds of Mercy; never to return any more to Folly. 'Tis not Bells and Bonfires, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for thy past Follies, and new Obedience thy God looks for at thy hands.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:206130:13"/>(5.) Lastly, Then do we act becomingly to the Mercies of God, when Mercies already brought forth, do encourage and strengthen our faith for those that remain still in the Womb of the Promises. So it was with <hi>Moses</hi> in my Text, and Oh that it might be so with us all! Our greatest and best mercies are yet to come, but those we bless God for this Day are pledges and earnests of them. You see them not, neither did you see these you are now praising him for six months ago; hath he caused these Mercies to be brought forth, and will he shut up the Womb? hath he done things we looked not for, and shall he not be trusted farther than we can see? Look as the head of <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> was served into the <hi>Israelites</hi> Table in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, garnished about with rich Experiences of the Goodness and Faithfulness of God, that it might be food to their Faith in the Wilderness; so, much so are the Mercies and Deliverances of this day to be improved, for the encouragement of Faith for further and future Mercies.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>ƲSE.</head>
               <p>The Point before us is full of useful Instructions, Cautions and Counsels. Time will permit me to do little more than note them to you; because I have noted to you another point of Doctrine which should I omit, I should be wanting to the Duty of the Day, and your just Expectations. Well then, are the Mercies of God already perform'd, such great things? and do they require such a sense and improvement of them from us? then</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:206130:14"/>(1.) Take heed of slighting and despising the Mercies of God which are fresh and new before your eyes this day. There are two special duties incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on all the Saints under such Mercies as these, <hi>viz.</hi> to observe the Lords Providences, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound his praises, and the later depends upon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. God can have no praise, we can have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from unobserved or slighted mercies. <hi>Whoso is wise and will observe these things, even they shall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the loving kindness of the Lord, Psal.</hi> 107.43. A due observation of mercies will beget a due valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; and a due valuation of mercies is fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental to all your praises of God for them. Look upon the other side of these Providences, and think what your Condition had been, if the Lord had left your Estates, Liberties and Lives to the Wills and Mercies of your Enemies.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Cheek all Atheistical thoughts from this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment of the hand of God so seasonably interposing betwixt his People and their Destruction. <hi>Verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth. Psal.</hi> 58.11. Great and notorious is the Atheism of these times, all serious Piety is hiss'd and ridicul'd; the very exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence of a Deity, and Divine Providence is denied by some. But would men open their eyes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve what is before them this day, they would see enough to stop the mouth of Atheism for ever. Are these Fortuitous Hitts and Accidents, or the effects and productions of the wise and steddy Counsels of Heaven? <hi>The Lord is known by the Judgments that he executeth.</hi> But when his hand is lifted up men will not see. 'Tis convincingly clear the Hand of God,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206130:14"/>not the Power or Policy of Men hath done this. There was no power in the prevailing part, but what might with far greater probability be repelled by the other; no Policy in the one, but as great to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it in the other. But you see the Race is not to the swift, nor the Battel to the strong; 'tis the hand of God that disposeth these great Events.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Be not stagger'd if you should see new diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties arising in the way of Mercy, after God hath begun to do great things for his people. <hi>Moses</hi> and his People encounter'd many such difficulties after God had lifted up his hand in great signs and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for them in <hi>Egypt:</hi> and so may we, even when we are come upon the borders of our expected Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Let us not say we shall never be moved more; there is a great deal of filthiness in <hi>England</hi> yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged, many Corruptions to be removed; and let us not expect much tranquillity till God have refined and reformed us. When the morbifique matter is not well purged out of the Body Natural or Politick, there is danger of a Recidivation, or Relapse into the old Disease, which God in mercy prevent. Former sins and follies will cast us back into former straights and miseries. O let us not return again to Folly. We are now upon Trial once more how we will carry it under Mercies and Liberties, God forbid so great an opportunity as this for settling the Church and State upon the true Foundations of Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity should be lost. Take heed of a discontented Spirit under Gracious Providences lest you provoke the Lord to turn his hand of Judgment again upon you. Who could have thought that <hi>Jonah</hi> who was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206130:15"/>so lately in the <hi>Whales Belly,</hi> called <hi>the Belly of Hell;</hi> and was so greatly humbled there, and so miraculously and graciously delivered thence, should presently fall into a pet of discontent with God, and that for a Trifle, the withering of a Gourd? Yea, and which was worse, for his Mercy to others. Oh, we know not what manner of Spirits we are of. The greatest Mercies and Deliverances do not long please us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less our little by-interests be gratified.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Let <hi>England</hi> now study to do great things for God, who hath impressed his greatness upon the Mercies it enjoyes this day. O <hi>England,</hi> God hath done great things for thee; saved thee with a great Salvation; and he expects returns from thee suitable to thy great mercies and obligations. Let me say to thee, as <hi>Elihu</hi> to <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 36.2. <hi>Suffer me a little, and I will shew thee that I have yet to speak on Gods behalf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1) A National Reformation is now expected by the Lord, he hath strongly obliged us to it this day by so glorious and unparallel'd a National Salvation. 'Tis our reproach that a Land of Ministers, a Land of Bibles, a Land of peculiar Mercies; should be a Land swarming in every part of it with prophane <hi>Swearers,</hi> filthy <hi>Adulterers,</hi> beastly <hi>Drunkards,</hi> and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daring <hi>Atheists.</hi> Do we thus requite the Lord, Oh foolish People and unwise? thy God, O <hi>England</hi> is pleading with thee this day by the voice of mercy, drawing thee out of these puddles and pollutions by the Cords of Love, whilst he is pleading against the same sins in the Nations round about thee by Fire and Sword. He hath now set upon thy <hi>Throne</hi> a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206130:15"/>great Example of Vertue, to correct thy Lewdness, and effect thy Reformation. O <hi>England,</hi> wilt thou not be made clean? When shall it once be? When, if not now, under such strong inducements, and sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal advantages?</p>
               <p n="2">(2) The loosing of every yoke, and undoing of every heavy burden is now expected from thee. God hath loosed the Yoke of Popery from our Necks, which neither we nor our Fathers could bear; and God forbid we should lay any other yoke upon our brethrens Necks, than what Jesus Christ hath laid by his plain Commands upon all his Disciples; or make any thing a term or condition of Communion, which himself hath not made so.</p>
               <p>O let the Groans and Cryes of oppressed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences be heard no more from hence-forth in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Did not the Lord lately shake the Rod of our common Enemies over us all? Had we not an <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Court</hi> erected among us which made those to tremble, at whose Bars others had trembled. If our God have been so good to us, beyond all Examples or Expectations to deliver us from our Fears and Dangers; surely he expects that those who have found mercy, should be ready to shew mercy, else we must expect he will make good his threatning against us, <hi>James</hi> 2.13. <hi>He shall have judgment without mercy that shewed no mercy;</hi> or <hi>unmerciful Judgment,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be rendered; and the Instruments and Executioners of his Judgments are not so far off, but he can quickly hiss for them again, if we answer not the voice and call of Mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) An hearty and lasting Union amongst all that fear God is now justly expected from us. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206130:16"/>expect Union and Coalition betwixt the Godly and Ungodly, 'twill be as much as I can expect to see the wickedness of men restrain'd and curb'd by good Laws that they persecute not; but renewing Grace must change their hearts and destroy their inbred En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, before they close with the people of God in Love. Nor do I think <hi>supercilious Pharisees</hi> or <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious Bigots</hi> will inwardly, and heartily affect the sincere and spiritual Servants of Christ; 'twill be a mercy they cannot <hi>afflict,</hi> whom they do not <hi>affect:</hi> but I should hope that in such a time as this, all that love the Lord Jesus in sincerity, and are animated by the same Spirit of Grace and Adoption, should now every where depose their Wrath, compose their little differences; and that their hearts be now melted in the sense of these great and common Salvations, into more love and union than ever. Such returns as these, will be pleasing to the Lord, and the only me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of lengthening out <hi>England</hi>'s Tranquillity. And though my Infirmities as well as Age cut off my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of being much longer serviceable, or of enjoying long the mercies God is preparing for his People; yet I should account it an extraordinary mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to see these beginnings of mercy well improved in order to those greater and better ones. Which brings me to the last Observation, which next comes to be opened and applied, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">Observ. <hi>That the beginnings of Mercy and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the Church, are convertible into so many Arguments, and Pleas in Prayer for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and Consummation thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:206130:16"/>
               <p>The Point lies clear and obvious in the Text: to open it let us consider,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>What the Mercies were which are here called the beginnings of Mercy?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>What the greater Mercies were, he expected beyond</hi> Jordan?</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>How the former strengthen Faith in Prayer for the latter?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Why the compleating of Mercies begun is so desireable to the Saints?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. What those mercies were which are here called the beginnings of Mercy? and they were great and manifold: in this <hi>Catalogue</hi> are to be placed all the mercies they had received for forty years, from the day they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> unto this great deliverance at <hi>Edrei</hi> inclusively.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) God began to shew his great Power in their wonderful Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> with mighty Signs, and an out-stretched Arm. This Deliverance from <hi>Egypt</hi> was a Pattern or Model of the future De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances of his Churches in New Testament days. <hi>Micah</hi> 7.15. <hi>According to the days of thy coming out of the land of Egypt, will I shew unto him marvellous things.</hi> Which seemeth to have Relation to the time of the Restitution, and saving of all <hi>Israel.</hi> After the manner of <hi>Egypt</hi> also hath God begun to save the Gentile Churches from <hi>Rome,</hi> which is Spiritually called <hi>Egypt, Rev.</hi> 11.8. And this begun Deliverance from the <hi>Mystical</hi> is greater than that from <hi>Literal Egypt,</hi> and so much greater, by how much Spiritual Bondage and Slavery of mens Souls, is worse than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:206130:17"/>that on their bodies, the hand of God was evidently seen in that, and is no less admirable in this. The Wonders of the <hi>Reformation</hi> are like those in <hi>Egypt,</hi> wrought out by the mighty Hand and Power of God.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The Hand and Power of God was seen in making provision for them in all their Wilderness-Streights, after they came out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> There were no Tilled Fields, or Barns, no Storehouses in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, nor <hi>Shops</hi> to furnish them with Cloathes for forty years in the Desart. Yet God took care to sustain them. 'Tis said <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.21. <hi>Forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, so that they lacked nothing, their cloathes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not.</hi> And certainly it would furnish an admirable History of Providence, if the instances of God's Care over his poor scattered persecuted Saints were collected, and how the Lord hath sustain'd them from the beginning of the Reformation, though none were suffered to buy or sell that received not the Mark of the beast in their Foreheads, or right hands. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.17. their Enemies would have starved them, but their God hath wonderfully provided for them.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The Lord frustrated all the Plots of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to destroy them, and there was no Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against <hi>Jacob,</hi> nor Divination against <hi>Israel. Remember, O my people</hi> (saith God) <hi>what Balack King of Moab consulted, and what Balaam the Son of Beor answered him from Shittim unto Gilgal; that ye may know the righteousness of the Lord.</hi> They built many <hi>Altars,</hi> and offered many Sacrifices, what would they not have done, to have gotten but a word or two out of God's mouth against his People?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:206130:17"/>but their God was true and faithful to them, and would not hearken to <hi>Baalam</hi>'s insinuations against them. There have been Plots upon Plots to destroy the begun Reformation. <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted our Destruction, as they did theirs, but to no purpose.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) The Lord discomfited and defeated the open Force as well as the secret Treachery of their Enemies, and no Weapon formed against them ever prospered. The Kings, several Kings by whose lands they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> fell upon them in their way, but still to their own cost, they forfeited their Lives and Lands by their quarrel with <hi>Israel.</hi> And now the last of those Kings and Kingdoms that opposed their passage, is fallen into the hands of <hi>Israel:</hi> These were the Mercies wherein God had begun to show his Greatness to <hi>Moses</hi> and his People, and after the manner of <hi>Egypt,</hi> unto us also.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But what were the greater Mercies he expected beyond <hi>Jordan,</hi> which he so vehemently desires to see? and in comparison wherewith he stiles all these great things but the beginnings of Mercy? Certainly <hi>Moses</hi> expected better things than these, as great and glorious as they were, and these were</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) The full and free Enjoyment of all God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which the people had not enjoyed for Forty Years before. All that were born by the way were not Circumcised, <hi>Jos.</hi> 5.5. and for the <hi>Passeover</hi> we find but three of them celebrated all that space, the first in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 12. the second at <hi>Mount Sinai, Numb.</hi> 9. the third at <hi>Gilgal</hi> in <hi>Joshuah</hi>'s time, <hi>Jos.</hi> 5.10. and as for their other Sacrifices and Offerings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206130:18"/>appointed by the Lord, they were either omitted, or very disorderly performed, which because of their many troubles, and frequent removes, they could not enjoy; and when they did, they were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as he required, which the Lord smartly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked them for, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.25. <hi>Have ye offered unto me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, O house of Israel?</hi> No they had not, at least not in the due order, as God required. But when they should arrive to a settled condition in <hi>Canaan,</hi> then the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God should be more frequently enjoyed, and that after the due Order, for so <hi>Moses</hi> had told them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.8, 9. <hi>Ye shall not do after all the things that we do here this day, every man whatsoever is right in his own eyes; for ye are not as yet come to the rest, and to the inheritance which the Lord your God giveth you.</hi> When they should be settled in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the Ark find rest, <hi>Moses</hi> knew that all things should then be reduced to the Rule and Pattern God had given them. And truly nothing is more beautiful, more desireable in the eyes of the Saints. For so much of God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as is found in his Worship, so much of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and Blessing may be expected, and no more. And as he expected more purity in Ordinances, so</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Rest and Peace was expected in <hi>Canaan,</hi> a Mercy the People had long wanted. The <hi>Ark</hi> had been ambulatory a long time, removing now here, now there: but in the Temple it was to find rest. Therefore you read in <hi>Psal.</hi> 132.8. the Temple called the place of rest; <hi>Arise O Lord into thy rest, thou and the Ark of thy strength,</hi> because there it was to have a fixed abode. And as the Ark was there to find a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:206130:18"/>place of rest, so the people also, who instead of <hi>Tents,</hi> should now be placed in Towns and Cities.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) But especially that which <hi>Moses</hi> desired to see in <hi>Canaan,</hi> was the fulfilling and accomplishment of the promises of God made to the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> in the Faith and Comfort whereof they lived and died. This Priviledge <hi>Joshuah</hi> enjoyed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Not one thing hath failed, all are come to pass.</hi> O what a lovely and desireable sight was this?</p>
               <p>But in these latter dayes, we for, whom better things are provided look for greater Mercies, than <hi>Moses</hi> and the people could expect in <hi>Canaan.</hi> For we according to the Promises expect,</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) An abundant increase of the Church, both <hi>extensively,</hi> in the number of Converts; and <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively,</hi> in the power of Religion. The best Ministers every where complain with the Prophet, that they labour in vain, and spend their strength for nought. They now and then at best hear but of a single Soul wrought upon; but the time will come, when they shall not fish with Angle-Rods, but spread out their Nets, and inclose multitudes. According to that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious promise, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.10. and as to the <hi>intensive</hi> increase of the Church in the Spirit and Power of Godliness, we expect to see a Generation of more Spiritual, Active, and Lively Christians to spring up. Such as shall far excel those of this drowsie, lukewarm Generation, according to that promise: <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Thy people also shall be all righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Greater peace and quietness from persecuting Enemies, is yet to be expected. The poor Church hath been afflicted, and tossed with Tempests. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors have broken in ever and anon upon it, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:206130:19"/>made havock of it; a tender Conscience hath cast men upon great difficulties to preserve it, but the dayes are coming when God will give his Churches rest, either by the Conversion, or restraint of all its Enemies: <hi>the wolf shall lye down with the lamb.</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies shall be deposed, <hi>Isa.</hi> 11.6. not a pricking Briar or grieving Thorn, that shall not be rooted up, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.24. Surely this is a sweet and desireable mercy to the weary Saints, and yet a far sweeter mercy than that is to be expected, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The pouring out of the Spirit of Unity upon the people of God to consolidate and strengthen the poor dilacerated Church. For the divisions of <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben,</hi> there have been great thoughts of heart. Our Divisions have darkned the lustre of Religion, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bittered and spoiled the Communion of Saints, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced the World, and obstructed Conversion. But God will melt the Hearts of the Saints into one, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. They shall have one Heart, and one way, and serve the Lord with one consent. Then shall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion shine in its Native Glory. One reason of our justlings one against another hath been the darkness that hath been upon us all. But this darkness shall break up: for</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) We expect a more Spiritual and Excellent Ministry than the Church for many years hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed; <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I will give you Pastors according to mine heart, which shall feed you with knowledge, and understanding.</hi> 'Tis a sore plague and judgement upon the World, when men shall be set over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that are ignorant of Regeneration, Strangers and Enemies to practical Holiness; Men that break their prophane Jests upon the very Spirit of Prayer.
<pb facs="tcp:206130:19"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:206130:20"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:206130:20"/>but these unclean Spirits shall pass out of the Land, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.2. O what a good riddance will this be! When God shall set up in their room laborious faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and godly Ministers, full of experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Christ. Watchmen that shall see eye to eye, as he speaks <hi>Isa.</hi> 52.8. Then shall we see another most desireable and inestimable Mercy perform'd to the Church, beyond all it hath enjoyed since the primitive dayes, namely,</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) The purity of Ordinances and Officers in the Church, the whole Worship and <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the Church measured by the Scripture Reed, according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.11. all reduced to the pure primitive Rule and Standard, which will disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and correct the oblique and corruptive superad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men. Things under which men of tender Consciences, and such as tremble at the Word, in all Ages have groaned. And then will the Ordinances of God shine forth in their Beauty, and be mighty in power and efficacy. Especially when</p>
               <p n="6">(6.) There shall be a more eminent presence of God among his People. For so it is promised, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48. <hi>ult. And the name of the City</hi> (viz. the measured regulated Church) <hi>from that day shall be the Lord is there.</hi> This is the true Glory of the Church; this makes the new Heavens and the new Earth, which according to his Promise we look for, and the great and marvellous things our Eyes behold this day are the beginnings and introductions to it; which brings us to the third General Head, namely,</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) What influence these begun works of God have to strengthen and encourage our souls in Prayer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:206130:21"/>for these greater and more perfect Mercies! and this they do upon a threefold account.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) As these begun introductive works of Mercy are indications and signs that the time of Mercy, even the set time is come.</p>
               <p>There is an appointed or set time for the Churches Deliverance now, as well as for theirs out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> that was called <hi>the time of the promise, Acts</hi> 7.17. Deliverance can neither come before it, nor will it linger, when that time is fully come. Promises like a pregnant woman, have their appointed Months, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. Their set and appointed time, <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.13. Now, when we behold such things done, and doing in the World; as are at this day before our eyes, we may rationally conclude the time of Mercy even the set time is near; as our Saviour speaks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.32, 33. <hi>Learn a parable of the figtree, when his branch is yet tender, and putteth forth leaves, ye know that Summer is nigh: so likewise ye, when ye shall see all these things, know that it is near; even at the door.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, it is a singular encouragement in Prayer, when we know, or can but probably conjecture that the time is near for the accomplishment and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of those very promised Mercies we pray for. As we see in <hi>Daniel, Chap.</hi> 9.2, 3. when <hi>Daniel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood by searching and studying the Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, such Prophesies as that <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.11, 12. that the time foreset was near at an end, then he set him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with extraordinary fervency to Prayer. And do not the generality of learned and good men agree, that the set time for <hi>Romes</hi> destruction is now near, even at the door? 'Tis near 1260 years since Christ turned up her Glass, and you see this day all things
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:206130:21"/>working towards the accomplishment of the written Word. This cannot but be a strong encouragement to seek God by Prayer for the full accomplishment of what is so near us.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) God hath ordered the Deliverances and Mercies of his Church to be birthed out by the Cries and Prayers of his People. When therefore Mercies are come to the Birth, 'tis a special season, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular encouragement to Prayer. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.36, 37. <hi>I the Lord plant that that was destroyed, I have spoken it, and I will do it, thus saith the Lord God, yet for this will I be enquired of by the house of Israel, to do it for them.</hi> So again in <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11, 12. <hi>I know the thoughts that I think towards you, saith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evil; to give you an expected end. Then shall ye call upon me, and ye shall go and pray unto me; and I will hearken unto you.</hi> In both these places, you see God will have Prayer to assist the Birth of Mercy; and never is any Mercy so sweet, as when Prayer comes betwixt our Dangers and Deliverances; our wants, and supplies. Hence it was that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> sent that seasonable Message to the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Lift up a cry for the remnant that is left, for the Children are come to the birth, and there is no strength to bring forth.</hi> If ever men will strive with God to purpose in Prayer, 'tis when they perceive the greatest Mercies are at the Birth, and Prayer is the Midwife to bring it forth.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) When God hath begun a work of Mercy, it gives singular encouragement to Prayer, because that time is the time of finding a proper and acceptable Season; as it is <hi>Psal.</hi> 32.6. <hi>For this shall every one that is godly pray unto thee, in a time when thou mayest
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:206130:22"/>be found.</hi> Or in a time of finding. <hi>Courtiers</hi> who have great Requests to make to Kings, do carefully observe their <hi>mollissima fandi tempora,</hi> as they call them; their convenient seasons when they find the King most propense and inclinable to Acts of Grace. That which is in motion, is the more easily moved. God is now in the way of Mercy. His Goodness is moving spontaneously towards us, and if ever Prayer be like to speed and prevail, now is the time. And in the last place.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Manifold and weighty are the Reasons and Motives that should fully engage the most fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires and Prayers of all the Saints to see the full Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of <hi>Sion;</hi> and to pass over <hi>Jordan,</hi> to behold that goodly Mountain and <hi>Lebanon.</hi> I mean those six glorious Mercies and Priviledges before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
               <p>First, The Saints Love to Christ makes it above measure desireable to them. Nothing is more dear and precious to a Christian, than the Glory and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of Christ; and answerable to the strength of their Love, is the fervor of their Desires. 'Tis said <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.16. <hi>When the Lord shall build up Sion, he shall appear in his glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilst the Church groans under Antichrist, the Glory of Jesus Christ is darkned and much eclipsed in the World. It hath been the chief part of the Saints Sufferings to see his Ordinances polluted, and the Rights of Heaven invaded by the Usurpations of Men; this is it that hath cost them more sorrow of Heart than their personal Sufferings have done. But to see the accomplishment of that Prophesie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. what will it be, but as life from the dead? <hi>And the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:206130:22"/>Temple of God was opened in Heaven, and there was seen in his Temple the Ark of his Testament,</hi> &amp;c. as it was an exceeding joy to the Godly in <hi>Israel,</hi> when good <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah</hi> came to the Crown, to see the Temple opened, which had been neglected in the dayes of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors <hi>Manasseh</hi> and <hi>Amon,</hi> in whose Reigns the Book of the Law had lain in the rubbish, but now the worship of God was restored; so it cannot but ravish a gracious heart with singular delight and joy, to see the pure Primitive Worship of God restored to its first Purity and Glory: And the more any man is sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the more he is inflamed with desires after it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Glory of Christ is so much interested and concerned therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their love to the <hi>Church,</hi> of which they are Members makes this greatly desirable. <hi>Moses</hi> was a Man who excelled in love to the Church, witness that transcendent rapture of his, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. but though he be scarcely imitable therein, yet every real Christian doth in his right frame prefer <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to his chief joy. <hi>Psal.</hi> 137.5, 6. and accordingly, their love to <hi>Zion</hi> is evidenced in their Prayers for and desires of its prosperity. <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.2. <hi>For Zions sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalems sake I will not rest, until the righteousness thereof go forth as brightness; and the salvation of it as a lamp that burneth:</hi> So again, <hi>Psal.</hi> 122.8. <hi>For my brethren, my companions sake I will now say, peace be within thee:</hi> For when the Church shall be delivered from the Antichristian yoak, and setled in peace and purity, great will its increase be. Her Children shall say again in her Ears, the place is too straight, give room that we may dwell. She will look forth as the Morning, and her glory be fresh in her.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:206130:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The pity and compassion the Saints have for the poor, miserable, perishing World cannot but make this a desirable thing in their Eyes. For whilst the Gospel is restrained in its full liberty, or the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances corrupted by the mixture of Humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Traditions; 'tis not to be expected that the Church should be much enlarged by addition of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of our Lord Jesus is for present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within straight and narrow limits; and it is just matter of sorrow to consider, how small a part of the habitable World is in subjection to him. So many Millions bowing down to Idols; the dark places of the Earth, are full of the habitations of Cruelty, <hi>Psal.</hi> 74.20. the sight of precious Souls perishing for want of the Word, made the bowels of the Compassionate Redeemer to yearn within him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.36. and the same consideration and occasion cannot but affect and melt every Soul in which is the Spirit of Christ, proportionable to the compassions Men have for the miseries of the perishing World, will their desires be for the enlarging and perfecting of Gospel Priviledges and Mercies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Love to our selves will make us long for such a sight as this: For what is there in this World more pleasant to a Christian, than to see Christ walking amidst the Golden Candlesticks? The peaceful and sweet enjoyment of God in his pure Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? <hi>Psal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>One thing have I desired of the Lord, that will I seek after, that I may dwell in the house of the Lord all the dayes of my Life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his Temple.</hi> This was <hi>Davids hoc unicum,</hi> one thing above all other things
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:206130:23"/>in this World in his Eye, and so it is to all that see things with such an Eye as <hi>David</hi> had; and next to that is the sweet and comfortable communion of Saints, with one heart and mouth glorifying God, and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him with one consent. These are the things that make it worth while to live on Earth: The pleasure of Life doth consist in them. Now all these desirable things cannot be enjoyed in any eminent degree on this side <hi>Jordan,</hi> I mean till the great promises now near their birth, be accomplished.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ƲSE</hi> 1. This point before us frowns upon, and severely reprehends two sorts of persons, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Wicked.</item>
                  <item>2. The Godly.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">(1.) It administers just reprehension to wicked men, who instead of thankful acknowledgments of the beginnings of mercies, and improving them in Prayer for the obtaining of greater, do inwardly repine and fret at the Work of Mercy begun, and are afraid of nothing more than a full and compleat reformation. Are there not such wretched Creatures to be found this day in <hi>England,</hi> that would be better pleased to be at their old persecuting work again, and see good men destroyed, than to enjoy a due liberty to worship God according to the dictates of their Consciences; after they have seriously studied and pray'd for informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Some there are who call themselves <hi>Protestants,</hi> but (blush O Heavens at this, and be astonished) they have not been ashamed to say, <hi>rather Popery, than Presbytery:</hi> And <hi>Haman</hi> like, take no comfort in their own liberty, because those they hate injoy theirs.</p>
               <p>Thus it was with the ungodly <hi>Murmurers</hi> in <hi>Israel,</hi> when God had brought them out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:206130:24"/>Signs and Wonders, and a mighty hand, yet their lusts being crossed, they would needs make them a <hi>Captain,</hi> and return back to <hi>Egypt, Numb.</hi> 14.4. What madness was here? Could they think God would divide the Red Sea for them in their return to <hi>Egypt,</hi> as he did at their departure thence? Or that they should find such welcome in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which they had deserted, disobliged, and brought so much ruine upon? What stupendious madness was here!</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) It justly rebukes the dead-heartedness and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of good men, amongst many of whom is neither found that fervency in Prayer, nor sense of present mercies which God expects, and the present dispensations of his Providences call for.</p>
               <p>How inexcusable at this time, is a flat, discouraged and dull Spirit in Prayer? To be found under such a temper as this, when the morning of so glorious a day is sprung up and opened upon us, such encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to enliven Faith and hope are before our eyes; this is sad: The Saints that are gone to Heaven under the late &amp; former troubles, were mighty wrestlers with God in Prayer: They fasted and wept; they pleaded our cause heartily with God, wept and made suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for the mercies we now enjoy; though it was not their lot to see them, and shall we that are entred into the Fruits and Mercies they prayed for, and are under such signal encouragements be now remiss and cold!</p>
               <p>Or shall we ingratefully overlook the beginnings of Mercy, as small and inconsiderable things? Shall we say all this is nothing, because we have not yet all that we would have? God forbid. When <hi>Israel</hi> was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> then a little Straw would have been estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:206130:24"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:206130:25"/>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:206130:25"/>as a great Mercy; but afterwards <hi>Quailes</hi> and <hi>Mannah</hi> were despised and slighted. Brethren, three or four years ago, you would have accounted it a special Mercy to have enjoyed an hour or two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Prayer, or to have had a little Spiritual Bread handed to you behind your Enemies backs: and is it nothing in your eyes this day, to behold the Worship of God at liberty? Yea, to see the success of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, in the bringing home of many Souls to Christ? The fears of Popery vanished? The Witnesses risen, the tenth part of the City fallen, and such a prospect of far greater and more glorious things before your eyes? O let not the Consolations of the Almighty seem small.</p>
               <p>If Wicked Men envy and grudge at our Mercies, and we our selves undervalue and slight them, then is there a grievous provocation given to the Lord, to turn his hand, and bring all our former Miseries back again upon us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ƲSE</hi> 2. Hath God brought us by a mighty hand out of Spiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> by the Reformation, and hath now led us so many years through the Wilderness, till he hath brought us at last almost in sight of the good things he hath promised; then let us be exhorted to the Duties, and warned of the Dangers of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent State.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Take heed of provoking God in the way. <hi>Moses</hi> did so, and for that was shut out of the good Land, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12. his heedlesness of the Command, deprived him of the good of the promise. Unbelief, Murmuring, and Idolatry shut out many thousands of them that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and for those Sins their Carkasses fell in the Wilderness. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:206130:26"/>And these are our Examples, not for imitation, but caution. When <hi>Seamen</hi> sail along the Coast, where abundance of wrack is floating, they sail the more warily. You are not yet so secure and safe, but that you may quickly fall into as great Dangers and Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as ever, if you provoke the Lord in the way of Mercies. In the miscarriage of others we get expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience at a cheap rate. After great Deliverances, the greatest Judgments are to be feared, if God be provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the abuse of them. So <hi>Joshua</hi> tells them, <hi>Jos.</hi> 24.20. <hi>He will turn again, and do you hurt, after he hath done you good;</hi> for one Mercy can never be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as an Argument to obtain another, if it be abused and trampled under feet: So <hi>Jos.</hi> 23.15. and <hi>Jude</hi> 12.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Be not discouraged if you should meet with some difficulties, even on the borders of the Land of Promise. After all their Wilderness-straights, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance at the Red Sea, encounters with the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kings; there was a swelling <hi>Jordan</hi> at last betwixt them and the place of rest and Mercy; and so it may fall out with us; but let not our Faith be stagger'd, for look as the <hi>Ark</hi> of the Covenant stood in the midst of <hi>Jordan</hi> to secure the <hi>Tribes</hi> in their passage through it, <hi>Jos.</hi> 3.8. so doth the promise stand this day in the midst of Mystical <hi>Jordan,</hi> I mean the Dangers and Troubles of the Church to secure its pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage through them all. Brethren, follow ye the Lord in the way of Duty, and you shall assuredly find that <hi>Jordan</hi> shall divide when you come to it; and that all Troubles, all Fears, all Difficulties do owe you a safe passage through them; the Covenant, yea, Christ the Mediator of the Covenant stands in the midst of them all to secure you.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:206130:26"/>(3.) Bless God for casting the lot of your Nativity upon such an happy and extraordinary period of time as this is. Many Saints have desired to see the dayes you are likely to see in a little time, and have not seen them. The whole space of time from the first to the second coming of Christ, is by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets called one day, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.7. and the greatest part of this long day, very doubtful and changeable; neither light, nor dark, nor day, nor night: Peace and Trouble; Truth and Errors taking all along their alternate Courses. <hi>But at Evening time it shall be light:</hi> And as the greatest darkness is a little before the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Morning; so here, the blackest and gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miest part of the whole day is to be expected before this lightsome glorious Evening; such tribulations immediately before the fall and ruine of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as ages past never saw. <hi>Lactantius</hi> speaking of this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time, <hi>That a little before it, the State of Humane Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs must necessarily be changed, and all things grow worse and worse; so that these times of ours</hi> (saith he) <hi>in which iniquity is grown as one would think to the height, yet in comparison with those dayes may even be called gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den times; the Godly shall be every where distressed by the wicked, they shall flourish, and the righteous be in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; all Right and Law shall perish and be confounded; no man shall possess any thing but what is ill gotten, or valiantly defended; there shall be no faithfulness in men; no peace, humanity, shame, or truth left: Wars shall rage every where; all Nations shall be in Arms; neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cities shall war upon each other; then shall slaughters be in all the World, mowing down all like an harvest; of which confusions and destructions, this shall be the cause: I tremble to speak it, (but it must be spoken, for it shall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:206130:27"/>surely come to pass) that the</hi> Roman <hi>name by which the World is now ruled, shall be taken away from the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These things in themselves are exceeding dreadful, and yet I say, let the Saints rejoyce in that God hath cast their lot upon these times. For</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) These are the last Troubles the Church is like to feel from the hands of that Enemy, and there is much comfort in that. God never exercised so great Patience and Long-suffering towards any Enemy of his Church as he hath towards this. But the day is come to avenge the blood of the Saints upon <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and destructions are come, even come to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual End.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The Lord will take care of his people in all these Calamities, and National Confusions. They shall be reserved as a Seed to continue and inlarge the Church, which is to be the subject of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised Liberty and Glory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Labour to get suitable frames of spirit to those good Times you expect. Carnal Hearts will not suit them, or find any pleasure in them. We look ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promise for new Heavens, and a new Earth wherein dwelleth Righteousness; and seeing we look for such things, oh what manner of persons ought we to be! 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. You that are Parents, how are you concerned not only for your selves, but for the Religious Education of your Children. If you live not to see those good days, in all probability they will; the hopes of the next Generation depends much upon your Religious and Zealous Care and Diligence. Never were Children born in a more happy and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging time than yours is.</p>
               <p>And for you young ones, I would leave one word
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:206130:27"/>of Counsel this day. Get Principles of Grace im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in your hearts betime. For the days are coming in which this World will be no place of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure for prophane and carnal persons. As serious Piety hath been hissed at and ridicul'd in these late debauched times, so will prophaneness in future times. <hi>Holiness to the Lord shall be upon the bells of the Horses, Zech.</hi> 14.20. That is, <hi>Husbandmen</hi> shall have their Hearts in Heaven, whilst their Hands are on the Plow. <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Seamen,</hi> shall drive a trade for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as well as Earth, <hi>Isa.</hi> 23.18. <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.5. If you be prophane and ungodly, you shall at once be the contempt of Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Lastly, Bless God for those Instruments by which you are brought out of Spiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> to the borders of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You must not ascribe more to Instruments than is due to them, nor lean and depend too much on them. Many benumb their own Arms, by leaning on them. But on the other side, beware of Ingratitude to the Instruments by which God works out your deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and conveighs to you such excellent Mercies. Some know no other way of expressing their Joy but by drunken Healths and <hi>Huzza</hi>'s, a Sacrifice suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> but such as God abhors, and his Vicegerent will not thank you for. There are other ways of expressing your joy in the Mercy which will be highly acceptable both to God, and the King, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Pray for your Rulers, that God would make Kings to be Nursing-Fathers, and Queens Nursing-Mothers to the Church, according to that promise, <hi>Isa.</hi> 49.23. That he would preserve and secure the heart of the King by his Wisdom and Fear from those dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:206130:28"/>Temptations and Snares that surround the Throne. <hi>That he may be just, ruling in the fear of God, and so be as the light of the morning when the Sun riseth, even a morning without clouds; as the tender grass spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the earth, by clear shineing after rain,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3, 4. That the Zeal of God may inflame his Soul, and that he may be a second <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in restoring and reforming the Worship of God. That God would lengthen the days of his life upon the Throne, for the peace and prosperity of his Church. In this you will answer the great things God hath done for you, and his Church at this time.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Be Loyal, Peaceable and Obedient Subjects. Convince the World that Religion breeds the best Subjects. <hi>Render to Caesar the things that are Caesars, and to God the things that are Gods, Mark</hi> 12.17. where you enjoy Protection, you owe Allegiance. Be not <hi>Murmurers,</hi> as the ungrateful <hi>Israelites</hi> were, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. understand and value the Mercies you enjoy under the Government, and bless God for them; lest he teach you by sad Experience the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his service, and the service of the Kingdoms of the Countries, as he did them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.8. Beware you exchange not the Golden Yoke of <hi>Christ</hi> for the Iron Yoke of <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Take heed to order your Conversations aright, let not your irreligious lives make the solemn Religious Duties of this day to blush. <hi>Whoso offereth praise, glorifieth me; and to him that ordereth his conversation aright, will I shew the salvation of God, Psal.</hi> 50. ult. And thus your present Mercies, how great and glorious soever they be in themselves; shall be but as the dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light of a much more Glorious Day springing up upon these Nations, and all the Churcches of Christ after so long and gloomy a night of Afflictions and Sorrows; which the Father of Mercies grant for the sake of Jesus Christ, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:206130:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>